[Music]
hey hey welcome back
it is day four of our camp uh i'm here
with my campers again let them introduce
themselves as always
neela hi i'm bowen yeah hi i'm keegan
hi i'm mckinley great so we've got a new
game for you today uh but before we get
into it let's just kind of quickly
review just a couple of the skills we
learned last time
uh yesterday's was our hardest game of
the camp uh it was this like
fish game going around you probably had
a different a different plan
and we learned all kinds of good skills
let's just kind of glance at some of the
skills that we learned
um we learned how to do race car
movements like changing our angle
but continuing to going forwards we
learned that we could draw
sprites um we learned that we could use
random numbers so like our objects
started off at random numbers
uh we learned how to broadcast events
last time so like when somebody hit him
they just said hey i hit him
we learned how to record custom sounds
like game over
um and we learned how to import images a
whole like
smorgasbord of skills last time we're
going to use a couple of those skills in
today's game
let's take a look at today's game so
it's called catching dinner
the theme of my game is that i have
avery again so i kind of like the avery
sprite um
and my avery is holding a basket and i'm
using the left arrow key to move her in
one direction
and the right arrow key to move her in
another direction and the goal is that
she's trying to catch things that would
be good for her to eat for dinner
so a taco a watermelon some bread those
are good things for dinner
but she tries to avoid things that would
be bad for dinner um in this case
the things that would be bad for dinner
is the the donuts right
um so i'm waiting for a donut to come if
i catch a donut
that's what finishes my game right so
that's the idea of this game
you can see that there's a score
involved and you try to catch as many
like good and healthy things as you can
but if you catch the bad thing
then it's game over before we dive in i
just want to point out that the
interesting thing about this game
is that there's one avery which is
probably what you would expect
but then there's only one sprite for the
good food
and only one sprite for the bad food so
how do we do that right because of
course there's like
all kinds of sprites falling um but
there's only one of them
down here and the nice thing about that
is that they all share the same code
which is cool but you're making clones
of them so if i was to make a clone of
myself i'd be like one of me
and then two of me and then four of me
and then eight of me uh there would be a
lot of clones
so we're gonna learn about cloning uh so
let's go ahead and
go to scratch so go ahead and go to
scratch.mit.edu
click on create and we'll start a new
game for today
so uh before we get started today uh
first i want to get rid of the cap
i want you to kind of do some of the
things to establish your theme and your
game
right up front so you can see that mine
is avery
avery is catching good foods and
avoiding bad foods decide what you think
your theme
should be and we're going to start off
by adding those sprites
so for me i want just avery so i'm going
to click on choose a sprite
and i'm going to go with avery right
here
if you want to you could choose to look
for something on the internet right so
if you wanted to get an image from the
internet uh remember last time how he
chose to like
do google searches and search for images
and then we went into tools and picked
ones with color transparency
you could do that if you wanted i'm not
going to do it here i'm just going to
pick avery
which is the sprite that i want i'm
going to resize avery a little bit
um and then what i choose to do is if
you look at my game i chose to give
avery
a bowl that she's holding how did i give
her a bowl that's kind of a sneaky thing
to do
i'm gonna show you how i did that if you
would like to give a bowl to your person
you can
but it is optional right so here's what
i'm going to do to to give her a bowl
i'm going to go into costumes
and i could try to draw a bowl but i'm
not a very good artist
so that would probably be a bad plan um
what i'm going to do is over here i'm
going to choose to
add a costume so over here you can add
sprites
and over here you can add more costumes
to the existing spray and that's a trick
we're going to use a lot today
so i'm going to say choose a costume
and i'm going to search for a bowl
so there's this bowl a that i found
now when i add the bowl it adds it as
like a separate sprite
but to fix that what you can do is you
can um highlight the whole area
and copy the bowl so i use ctrl c to
copy
come back into this one and ctrl v
to paste it in here and so you can see
that i can give her a bowl if i wanted
that's just a type of drawing trick that
you can use
where you add some other sprite and then
you kind of drag over the whole thing to
highlight it
and then you just use ctrl c to copy go
to where you want and control v
to paste now at the end of the day i
just want this one costume of avery i
don't need this one where she's standing
with her hands behind her back and i
don't need this one
i can actually delete those costumes and
nothing bad will happen
so just kind of a little trick there the
next thing i do is i want to pick my
good items and my bad items
again your theme can be different than
mine but i'm going to choose to add
foods as my good items so i'm going to
click on choose a sprite
uh and i'm gonna add one food maybe i'll
add the apple first
now um if you look at my game over here
here's what i did that was sneaky over
here is i added one food you can see i
added a taco first
and then i added a bunch of different
costumes to that one sprite
we're going to do the same thing so i've
got an apple
an apple currently has one costume in
him
and i'm going to choose to add more
costumes i'm going to add other costumes
of my sprites so maybe i'll go into food
and i'll just add a few foods right so
bananas
is a good food what's another good food
that i've got here i had tacos in my
other one maybe i should add a taco to
this one as well
tacos are delicious and then i'll add
one more just for fun
so i'll go to food and i'll have
i want it to be a good like healthy
thing watermelon looks like a good thing
to eat
so we're using costumes in a different
way this time you can see that i've got
one sprite and four different costumes
so costumes this time sometimes we use
costumes to make like animations but
this time we're like making it look
totally different
one one trick you do have to be careful
of is they do need to be roughly the
same size so you can see my apple
and my banana and my watermelon they're
all about the same size
but look at my taco it's kind of huge
right so if sometimes i show an apple or
sometimes i show a banana or sometimes
there's a watermelon that's fine but
then when i put the taco on it's
gigantic
you could make it smaller so i could
like make it smaller over here
but the problem is is that it makes my
apples and my bananas smaller so
with this trick you will occasionally
have to grab one
of them highlight the whole thing and
make them be roughly the same size
such that if you go between the apple
the banana the taco or the watermelon
they're all roughly the same size and
that i'm actually really happy with
so that's my good food my good food
right now is called apple
i'm going to change it to be a good item
if you don't want to change yours you
don't have to i just wanted to point out
you can change the names of your sprites
like avery here
in my mind she's my hero so whatever my
hero is i just name it hero
and then this is my good item next i
want to add a bad item
so i'm going to click on choose a sprite
and i'm going to pick a bad item what
i'm going to do is i'm going to pick
something that you would have for
dessert not for dinner
so i'm going to add donuts as my bad
item
and then i'm going to choose to rename
mine as bad item
and i'm going to make it roughly the
same size as my good item
now this style of coding is a little
different than what i've done before i'm
just kind of like getting my game
set up to start with and then i'm going
to start writing the code
and i'll just be able to knock things
out the other thing i want to do is i
want to backdrop
so i'm going to choose backdrop i think
in mine i actually picked like a jungle
theme
so i'll stick with the jungle for this
as well great
um so i'm going to pause it and i'm
going to let my campers get all their
objects figured out and then we'll start
in on the code so you can pause it and
you can get all your things figured out
so one hero
the good item has a variety of costumes
uh and then my bad item has only one
costume
all right see if you can make yours look
like mine all right so all my campers
got their heroes figured out they got
their various good items figured out uh
they got their badass and figure out
took us a little bit but we got there uh
let's dive into the code
um and i'm gonna start off with avery
which is our hero
so go ahead and find your uh your hero
whoever your hero is mine's avery
and let's go into the code this sprite's
going to be kind of the most similar to
things we've done in the past it's going
to start with
an event uh of when green flag clicked
so go and take a win green flag clicked
and bring it over
you could set her starting position if
you wanted to be the middle uh that's
optional i think i will go ahead and do
it so i'm going to go ahead and
find this go to xy
that way i'm guaranteed that she always
starts the game in the very middle
that's optional it doesn't really matter
but there's no harm in doing it
and then i'm going to do what i've done
so many times i'm going to make a
forever loop
so i'm going to drag out a forever loop
and snap it on here
you'll notice that this pattern happens
in a lot of our games when the green
flag is clicked
do some initialization things and then
do
some things forever the thing we're
going to do forever is we're going to
listen for
the left arrow and the right arrow and
so if the left arrow is pressed we'll
move to the left
if the right arrows press will move to
the right so we're going to add two if
statements
so drag two if statements number one
and number two
and then inside the if statements i want
to put a condition
so the condition that i care about is
the key press
so i'm going to go into sensing i'm
going to find
a key space pressed
and then of course it's got a little
white down arrow next to it
and so i'm going to click on this little
white down arrow and i'm going to change
it to left arrow for the top one
and then i'm going to change it to right
arrow for the bottom one
and again if you ever need to pause it i
mean definitely just pause the video
um and then you can get uh right cut up
door i'm doing
now inside left arrow and right arrow in
the past i've always done like
point in direction and then move some
amount
we could do that again but i'm just
going to show you an alternative
i'm going to just change the x value so
the x value is like the horizontal value
so i'm going to go into motion and for
both of these i'm going to have a change
x by so go and grab a change
x by and drop it into both places
now right now if you were to run the
game
um positive x would move to the right so
so the right arrow would work
it would be good but the left arrow is
not going to work
so campers what do i need to type in
here instead of ten
negative two yeah so i need to put in a
negative ten that's right
now the fun thing about this game is
that um avery's essentially done
um so i could run it and i could see if
i'm happy with that speed
so i hit on the go button and then if i
hit the right arrow should move to the
right
if i hit the left arrow she'll move to
the left
and so i think that avery is actually in
pretty good shape
we're going to have to check to see if
certain things are hitting her
but actually other sprites are going to
have that responsibility
her whole goal is just to move left and
right so she's kind of just like a
paddle
uh in a game another thing that we could
do if you wanted to do is we could make
a variable out of her speed
and so we could make make her variable
make her speed be a variable
and then we could set it once and use it
both places but honestly if it's just
these two right here
it's extra work to make a variable
so the next thing i want to do with
avery done is i want to save my game
so i'm going to call my game catching
dinner
if you want a different name for your
game that's just fine
but i'm going to type that in as my name
it does automatically save so you don't
have to do anything
else or you could hit file save now
and i'm going to help my campers type
some for the names of their game
all right so with avery doing well the
next thing i want to do is i want to be
able to make
food so i want to be able to make good
items and eventually bad items
now interestingly who should make the
foods
we could put that code on the hero's
right that would be fine
but i'm going to show you that you can
also put it on the stage so click over
here where it says stage
and you'll notice that the stage has
backdrops which we've already set a
backdrop on it
but a stage also has code so you could
totally put code in the backdrop
and that's what we're going to do this
time and so we want to go to events
we want to find when green flag is
clicked
and the code that the stage is going to
run is it's going to be
responsible for creating the good items
and the bad items
so he's going to also have a forever
loop so let's go to control
forever
and what the stage is going to do is
he's going to make a new good item every
second
so every second he's going to stick
another one on the screen
the way that he does that is first he
has a wait for one second
so he waits for a second and then he
does something and the thing that he
does it's actually in control here
scroll down and control
and find where it says create clone
of now we want to create a clone of not
the hero
but of the good item eventually we'll do
good and bad items but for now we're
just going to do good items
and so the neat thing about this is that
if you run it
it will actually create a clone of
whatever your good item is mine is
currently set to a watermelon
now the question is where will it put it
right we can run it and we can see what
it does by default
so it's creating a clone of my
watermelon it's not very exciting
because it appears as though it's
making it right on top of the old
watermelon right so that's not much fun
so let's make it more interesting so
let's make the watermelon like go to
some position when it starts
so the stage is done now go into the
watermelon
now we're going to do something very
different here normally we start with
this
this event for when green flags clicked
that's
not what we're going to do this time
we're going to start with a different
event
it's down here in control and it's when
i start
as a clone so whenever i stars a clone
i'm going to do some stuff so this is
different than what we've done before
the things that i want to do i want to
go to some x position some x exposition
at the top of the screen
so i'm going to go somewhere up here so
here's what i'm going to do i'm going to
take my good item and i'm going to move
it to roughly the top
just like somewhere near the top and
then i'm going to go to motion
and i'm going to find this go to xy
now if you think about what this game
does as it's playing is all things start
at the top
but they kind of start randomly along
the top
somewhere along the top so how do we do
that
so this would make it always go to that
spot which is no good
we want to go to a random x at this
y which is nearly at 180 right so to get
a random value we click on operators
inside operators find pick a random
number
and the random values for x if we
remember
from from previous days this uh screen
goes from
negative 240 which i guess i could just
move this over here and i can kind of
see that so it goes from like
negative 240 all the way over
to positive 240. so i want to pick a
random number from negative 2 4 0
to positive 2 4 0.
so now uh whenever we run this game a
new watermelon should show up somewhere
along the top so i took my original and
i kind of moved it back to here
so now when you run your game uh every
second a new watermelon should show up
at some random position
and so they're just kind of collecting
up there they're not moving
they're just they're just collecting
by the way mine's a watermelon just
because that's the costume that i've
currently clicked on if i click on an
apple
and i run it again then all my apples
are going to show up at the top
so it's kind of neat how it's the same
sprite it's just going to have a
different costume
all right let's do some more things with
our good item so we don't want it to
always be
uh an apple or always be a watermelon we
want to switch
what it is so let's go into looks
uh let's go into switch costume 2
and this is kind of tricky about scratch
it looks like there's a drop down arrow
here and you can actually
pick like you know apples if you wanted
to be apples but then they'd all be
apples or bananas and it'll be animals
we want to pick a random costume so go
into operators
find this pick random
and the fun thing about switch costume 2
is it can also receive a number
so you can see that i have four costumes
and there's a little number up here
one two three or four
so i can refer to them by their name or
their number which is really handy
so i want to pick a random number since
i have four costumes
one two three four i'm going to pick a
random number from one to four
and so this is going to pick a random
position and then a random costume
now if i hit the play button what
happens is it's not always an apple
sometimes it's an apple sometimes it's a
banana sometimes it's a taco sometimes
it's a watermelon
and your game should be able to do the
same thing and eventually the top will
get
really crowded with different food that
you might want to eat
great so we're doing really good
more initialization code i want them to
fall at a certain speed
um and i want that speed if we go look
at this one to not always be the same
right
so you can see how some fault that
watermelon just flew through
super fast right so they fall at
different speeds is our goal
so that's what we're going to do next
we're going to make a different speeds
um so i want to make a variable so we've
done variables many times
you click on variables click on
make a variable this variable
is going to be just for this sprite and
this is important because they can all
be different speeds right
so i'm going to call it just speed if
you wanted to you could call it fall
speed or good item speed
but i'm just going to call it speed i'm
say okay
and then what i'm going to do i want to
get rid of my variable i don't want my
variable in here i'm just going to right
click on it and say delete my variable
i like to delete it because then
whenever i drag something over
like if i drag over the set speed to it
it's going to default to saying speed
instead of my variable
and the speed we want is a random
variable uh which is uh kind of fun so
there's lots of random in this game
this is the fall speed this is how fast
does it fall
fall speeds should be negative and so
what i'm going to do is i'm going to do
a range of
negative 6 to negative 2. if you want
your stuff to potentially fall really
fast you could do negative 10 but that's
going to be really fast
if you wanted to fall really slow you
could do negative 1. but negative 6 is
pretty darn fast
and negative 2 is slow enough for me
so that's the full speed now we want to
actually start falling
so to actually start falling we need to
do something forever
so i'm going to put in a forever in here
and then i'm going to go into motion and
i'm going to find
change y by
so again today we're using this change x
y and change y
by which is just a little bit different
than move by
but change y by speed
so i'm going to go into variables and
put in speed
and i'm going to try to run it again and
so now they should all start falling
so now everybody shows up at the top uh
and then they start falling which is
cool
all right so things are going good by
the way what one of my campers had as a
problem is he accidentally put in a
switch backdrop too to insta switch
costume don't do that make sure it says
switch
costume too um so things are going good
but there's a few things that we need to
fix
one thing that's confusing is that my
original is sitting right here
right and my original actually doesn't
get used in the game
so here's what i want to do i want to
hide a couple things so i want to click
on my original which is the apple
and see how there's this show button
here so it's got like an eyeball or then
like an eyeball
crossed out i want to hide my original
now hiding your original is good um but
the problem is
is that all the clones of it are also
hidden right so that's easy to fix
so we hide the original and then in code
so in code we go into looks we find
where it says show
um and we just stick a show on here just
before the forever loop
so i i let it go ahead and pick its
position while it's still hidden switch
its costume while it's still hidden
set the speed while still hidden and
then i show it and then it starts to
fall the other thing i'm going to do
really quick is i'm going to go into
variables
and i'm going to check this box next to
speed because i
i don't need that showing up up there
right it doesn't really add anything to
the game
so now if i run it again you can see
that it has
different clones that fall so i've got
different clones that are falling
and my original is hidden right so
that's an important thing to do in these
games
now the next thing we want to do is that
if you catch one of these food
you'll see that nothing happens and also
you can see that when they get to the
bottom
nothing happens at the bottom either and
so we want to
if you catch one score point
and if it gets to the bottom we just
want it to disappear
and just not score any points for you so
let's go ahead and add those
um in code if we're trying to check for
different conditions those are if
statements
so in addition to falling we want to add
a couple of if statements so i'm going
to go into control
and i'm going to drag over an if
statement this top one's going to be for
like
if i'm touching the hero and i'm going
to drag over another if statement
and this bottom one is going to be for
like if i'm touching the bottom of the
screen
which we're just going to check the x
value getting so low
uh great so let's go ahead and put in
those two conditions the condition
for the first one is in sensing touching
mouse pointer
obviously touching mouse pointer is not
what we want but that's why there's this
little white drop down
and we're gonna switch it to if i'm
touching uh the hero
so i renamed avery earlier to be hero i
just typed her name in right there
so if we're touching the hero what
should happen
so let's go ahead and look at the the
solution over here and see what happens
well what happens is it scores a point
um
makes a pop sound um and makes it
go invisible there i touched the bad
item we'll get to the bad item
so there are like three things that will
happen fast we wanted to make a pop
sound so make some sound effect
let's go into sounds and see what sound
this one has right now mine has
chomp i guess i could play chomp chomp
is fine my
my original code played pop so i'm gonna
go into sound
i'm gonna say play chomp until done
so that's one thing we wanted to do the
next thing we want to do is we wanted to
score a point
so we're going to have to have a
variable for score so i'm going to go
into variables
make a variable
and this one's going to be called score
now score
is very different than speed score is
shared by everybody so anybody can
increment score there's only
one score in the whole game it's not
like everybody has their own individual
score there's one score so score
is for all sprites and i'm going to say
okay
now whenever you make a variable uh
there's a couple things you have to do
you have to create the variable which is
one
you have to initialize its value because
you don't want your score to like start
like where you left off the previous
game so we've got to initialize the
value somewhere
you can initialize its value in a lot of
places
the best place in my opinion is actually
back over in the stage so i know we're
working on the good food
but just for a minute i click over here
on the stage
so we're going to go over to his code
really quick
and i'm going to set score to zero
right after the green flag is clicked
and so this makes sense whenever the
game starts
my stage is code it's kind of like the
main code it's going to reset the score
to be zero
um and then the game is going to begin
with all these clones
all right so making the variable good
first step
initializing it to zero great next step
now let's go into your good item
and inside the good item we want to
change the score
so after we play our sound um or before
it doesn't really matter on the order
here
i'm going to put it before just because
i feel like it
so i'm going to change the score by one
i'm going to play a chomp sound
and i'm going to play it until it's done
just so you hear the whole sound
and then i'm going to disappear um and
the way we're going to disappear is
we're not going to hide
um we're going to go into control
and see where it says delete this clone
drag over and delete this clone
so easy comm easy to go so this clone
was made uh it fell
a little bit and then this one hit the
hero
it made a sound and then commanded the
score and then it got deleted
so let's try to play the game again try
to catch your first one that comes
i mean it should make a bite sound
and that's good now if you don't catch
them
something else happens they just end up
down here on the bottom right
and they end up down here in the bottom
you can actually just walk over and i
think you can still collect them from
the bottom right
that make the game kind of easy
so let's fix that so whenever they get
to the bottom or whenever they get
to a certain height we're going to say
hey you can no longer just walk over and
collect
them right so whenever they get to a
certain height that's going to be this
next if statement
we're going to just delete them and you
can't possibly score a point
so what we want to check for is we want
to check if
their y position is less than some
negative value
so uh the first thing i need here to go
in this diamond is an operator
for less than
so if the y position the y position
is something we can get from motion
so if the y position is less than some
number
the question is what's that number right
if you were to type in negative 180
that would actually be bad because that
would be like the very bottom of the
screen
so you could probably do like negative
that's just like a little bit up from
the screen or you could be like
really conservative and do like negative
160 which is what i think i'm going to
do
so i'm going to say if my y position is
less than negative 160
so i'm going to grab my donut and just
kind of show you where 160 is it's like
160 is
it's pretty low right so i guess my
donut can get
get there there it's negative 160 so
really low actually 160 may not
be conservative enough i'm gonna do 150.
so if you get below 150
which is about this height then i'm
going to delete
the clone so i'm going to go into
control
and i'm going to say delete this clone
try your game again
so if you catch them in the air you get
points
but if they get to the bottom uh they
just kind of disappear right
so you can see that they just disappear
which is good
great i'm actually really happy uh with
the good item
uh and things are things are going great
i'm gonna help my campers out
all right so the good item i think is in
pretty good shape
and now we're going to go through and do
the bad item so
the bad item uh just like we did before
it's going to get created by the
backdrop
so go ahead and click over here where it
says stage
and you can see that we've got code over
here so obviously
we create a good item now here's what i
want to do take this create good item
just set it over here to the side just
for a minute
and what we're going to do is sometimes
we're going to create good items
and then other times we're going to
create bad items right
now what our game is going to do is it's
going to randomly pick
a good item or a bad item to drop so
it's just going to randomly just like
drop one
so what i'm going to do is i'm going to
add an if else statement in here
and this condition we're going to come
back to it but sometimes we're going to
drop a good item
and then in the other situation we're
going to drop a bad item so
this condition is going to decide which
one it's going to be this time
and that's where if then and then else
statements can be good
so how do we make it drop good items
sometimes bad items other times
well we're going to use a combination of
operators
so we're going to use a less than symbol
again
and a random number so into this
the left-hand side we're going to put a
random number so we're going to pick a
random number
from 1 to 10 and if that number is less
than
uh maybe eight so if it picks one two
three four five six or seven
so it's drops a good item but if it
picks eight nine or ten
then drop a bad item right so if you run
it now
uh what should happen is it should drop
your good items and
it's making the bad items it is working
the code is working
um but they're they're not they don't
have any code yet right
so let's do this let's stop it
and let's see the bad items work now we
could write the code from scratch on the
bad item
but the code from the good item is so
similar that we should definitely just
use it to start with so here's what i'm
going to do
i'm going to take my good item code and
i'm just going to drag it over
and i'm going to drop it right on the
bad item you can see that kind of
wiggles when you get it on there
what that does is that just makes a copy
of it so now i've got my good item code
and then i come over here to my bad item
code and my bad item code
looks just the same it's kind of funny
how to the similar or how similar the
two are
really the only thing that changes is if
you're touching the hero
instead of scoring a point you want
something bad to happen
so i'm just going to temporarily take
this code out of there
in fact i can probably just drop it in
the trash can right
and i'm going to run it and see what
happens so now the bad item
should fall just like good items
the only difference is it won't score a
point right
it's like there i got the bad item but
nothing really happened
when i hit the bad item it just kind of
kept falling through me
now we've also got this problem of the
original bad item
is still just sitting on the screen see
if you can fix that problem all by
yourself
all right so i'm going to do what i had
to do really was just select the donut
and just
hide the original and so now there is no
original
so the donut doesn't do anything bad
when i hit it
so what i want to do is when i hit the
donut i want stuff to happen
since i want the whole game to stop
that's an excellent opportunity for us
to broadcast an event we've actually
learned about that before
it's over in events
and where it says broadcast message one
i want to drag this into my if statement
and instead of calling it message one
i'm going to give it a new
name so i'm going to say new message
and i'm going to type in a game over
so a broadcast message is really just
like somebody screams
game over right so whenever the
bad item touches the hero he screams
game over and everybody listens right
everybody listens everywhere this sprite
is going to listen for it so he's going
to have a
when i receive game over
and everybody is going to have but when
i receive game members so they all do
something including the stage
the first thing they're going to do when
they receive game over is they're gonna
stop their normal script that's a pretty
common thing
so that's in control near the bottom
and i find this a little confusing about
scratch it's the one that says stop all
and then you switch it to stop other
scripts in the sprite so
basically means once i receive game over
stop doing
whatever there was over here and i could
add that code
to to everybody i'm going to add it to
the good item
i'm going to add it to the hero i'm
going to add it to the stage everybody
kind of needs to do that much what the
heck i'll go ahead and do it now so i'm
going to drag it from here
drop it on the hero drop it on the good
item
and drop it on the stage i think it's
kind of cool how many people
uh there are with code in this i'm gonna
make sure that everybody's got that much
code
so my hero avery she's got it so
whenever she hears game over
she stops what she was doing uh that
that does that
the good item stops what they were doing
uh the stage even the stage has to stop
what the stage was doing so
every single sprite stops what they were
doing
and then they might do some other things
all right so let's try our code right
now uh and just kind of see what happens
uh so if i
collect uh good items so like tacos are
good
i get points but if i hit a doughnut so
i'm gonna hit a donut right here
um it just kind of freezes everything
now
interestingly everything freezes but
like it doesn't feel like the game was
over
so let's add like a sound effect uh or
something like that just to kind of let
people know it's it's game over
we have to decide who's gonna do that uh
we could have the hero do it we could
have the good item or bad iron do it
i think i'm gonna go to the stage so i'm
gonna go over to the stage
and i have the the stage kind of play
the the game over sound effect
so i'm gonna go into his sound um and
i'm going to look for a sound so i'm
going to click on choose a sound
i'm going to use the sound drum boing
um obviously you could pick a different
sound but i think drum bowing
um i think that that conveys the message
uh that you just
hit something you shouldn't have so i
added that to my sound so now i've got
drum blowing over there
then i'm gonna go into code keep in mind
i'm still on the stage
and i'm gonna go into sound i'm going to
say play
drum boeing what i'm going to do is i'm
actually just going to start it
and then i'm going to put on a time
delay for how long i want to wait
maybe i'll wait uh i don't know four
seconds
so i'm gonna play that boing and then
i'm gonna freeze for like four seconds
um and then after that four seconds i'm
gonna do a stop
all stop all is good because it'll
actually
clear all the sprites off so you'll
you'll hear this boing
uh you're gonna wait for about four
seconds and then you'll you'll clear off
everything
so i'm gonna go and try it and see if
it's working so i run it
i collect food um and it uh
now you can see that there's a little
bug of my food um
stayed on me for a little bit boing um
and then my game uh should end after
four seconds
four seconds felt a little long for me
maybe i'll do like
two seconds or three seconds or
something like that
great so i think that mine might be done
so i'm going to run it again here
collecting food so things that i should
eat for dinner
trying to catch my dinner and then if i
hit a donut
i get a boing and then i get a game over
cool
my game is done i'm going to choose to
click on
see project page um and i'm gonna
share it with other people now i've got
this url
uh that i could give to my grandparents
or things like that
by the way you can also put instructions
in here uh if you'd like to try to make
people uh know how to play your game
but i think mine is a done game so i'm
going to uh
see how my campers did all right neela
you're up first so what theme do you
have on your game today
oh you've got a dog that looks like our
dog neela
and then the dog you played again hit
the green flag again
what's the dog catching mila
catching the food and then who's the dog
trying to avoid
the zells those bats or whatever they
are
oh they're pterodactyls pterodactyls are
actually my favorite
type of dinosaur oh that's good to know
very nice
bone what have you got i've got a sock
a all right run it
oh a shirt oh yeah he's trying to avoid
a bottle
all right do it again green flag let's
see if we'll see you get a point
all right green flag though
all right let's see you get a point
cool they're catching lots of fish which
is great and then you just gotta avoid
the shark or the trash
nice work bowen
did you have fun making the game today
bo
pretty awesome
you're good all right mckinley what have
you got today um i made mine about
um unicorns and fruits and then i made
it so i can change
the speed so i can make my unicorn go
faster
or slower cool and then what's the
unicorn trying to dodge
oh yeah the parrots nice so you have an
evil parrot
uh and a unicorn looks wonderful very
nicely done
all right keegan what have you got today
so we've got a dog
and a dog's trying to catch bones oh or
fortune cookies
you've got a lot of things coming down
did you change how fast they came out
nope yeah i think you
because there's did lot of them cool so
the dog is trying to avoid the evil
squirrel
uh and then he's trying to catch bones
of things did you guys have fun today
yes you're a pterodactyl
all right well we hope you uh enjoyed
making a game today
uh we learned a lot of things like
changing x and y's
uh creating clones was our big thing um
and so that's it
uh hopefully you kind of learned the
main message that coding's fun uh you
can do this
and it really makes a lot of sense to
use like this one sprite
with lots of clones of it then that way
you can reuse the same code
instead of having to make lots of copies
of code alright we'll see you next time
friday i promise is a little shorter
hopefully you enjoy it
we're gonna see if we can convince
mckinley to lead the show tomorrow so it
should be fun
all right see you then bye